Admissions

ASSURED ADMISSION

First-time students who graduate from an accredited high school, have successfully demonstrated competency in the required five subject areas, and meet minimum performance requirements are assured admission to the University. These five subject areas are English, mathematics, natural sciences, social studies, and foreign language. Successful completion of a minimum of 16 core course requirements, either at the secondary school level or at the college level, is typically used to demonstrate competency. Performance requirements for freshmen include an ACT composite score of 20 or higher, or an SAT combined score of 950 or higher, or a high school class rank in the upper one-half of the graduating class. Several UNL undergraduate colleges require higher performance for admission into specific academic programs. See the college sections in this bulletin for more specific information about requirements. Prospective transfer students are also expected to demonstrate competency in the core course requirements, as well as have a cumulative grade point average of at least a C average (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and at least a C average in the last semester of college enrollment. Several UNL undergraduate colleges require higher grade point averages for transferring into specific academic programs. See the college sections in this bulletin for more specific information about transfer requirements.

DEFICIENCIES

Because admission requirements establish the level of knowledge and skills which are needed for a student to succeed at UNL, students who are admitted with core course deficiencies in foreign language and geometry are expected to quickly remove them. Deficiencies must be removed before a student is eligible for graduation.

General Education Requirements (ACE)

General Education Requirements (ACE)

http://ace.unl.edu

Consistent with the mission and values of the University, Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) is based on a shared set of four institutional objectives and 10 student learning outcomes. The ACE program was approved by faculty in all eight undergraduate colleges and endorsed by the Faculty Senate, the student government, and the Academic Planning Committee in January 2008 and implemented in the fall 2009. Key characteristics of ACE demonstrate the benefits of the program to students:

Students receive a broad education with exposure to multiple disciplines, critical life skills and important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.
ACE is simple and transparent for students, faculty and advisers. Students complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten student learning outcomes.
Students connect and integrate their ACE experiences with their selected major.
Students can transfer all ACE certified courses across colleges within the institution to meet the ACE requirement and any course from outside the institution that is directly equivalent to a UNL ACE-certified course. Courses from outside institutions without direct equivalents may be considered with appropriate documentation for ACE credit (see academic adviser).
ACE allows faculty to assess and improve their effectiveness and facilitate students’ learning.

ACE Institutional Objectives and Student Learning Outcomes

To meet the ACE Program requirement, a student will complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the following ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes (a total of 30 ACE credit hours):

Institutional Objective 1:

Develop intellectual and practical skills, including proficiency in written, oral, and visual communication; inquiry techniques; critical and creative thinking; quantitative applications; information assessment; teamwork; and problem-solving.

ACE 1: Write texts, in various forms, with an identified purpose, that respond to specific audience needs, incorporate research or existing knowledge, and use applicable documentation and appropriate conventions of format and structure.

ACE 2: Demonstrate communication competence in one or more of the following ways: (a) by making oral presentations with supporting materials, (b) by leading and participating in problem-solving teams, (c) by employing a repertoire of communication skills for developing and maintaining professional and personal relationships, or (d) by creating and interpreting visual information.

ACE 3: Use mathematical, computational, statistical, or formal reasoning (including reasoning based on principles of logic) to solve problems, draw inferences, and determine reasonableness.

Institutional Objective 2:

Build knowledge of diverse peoples and cultures and of the natural and physical world through the study of mathematics, sciences and technologies, histories, humanities, arts, social sciences, and human diversity.

ACE 4: Use scientific methods and knowledge of the natural and physical world to address problems through inquiry, interpretation, analysis, and the making of inferences from data, to determine whether conclusions or solutions are reasonable.

ACE 5: Use knowledge, historical perspectives, analysis, interpretation, critical evaluation, and the standards of evidence appropriate to the humanities to address problems and issues.

ACE 6: Use knowledge, theories, methods, and historical perspectives appropriate to the social sciences to understand and evaluate human behavior.

ACE 7: Use knowledge, theories, or methods appropriate to the arts to understand their context and significance.

Institutional Objective 3:

Exercise individual and social responsibilities through the study of ethical principles and reasoning, application of civic knowledge, interaction with diverse cultures, and engagement with global issues.

ACE 8: Explain ethical principles, civics, and stewardship, and their importance to society.

ACE 9: Exhibit global awareness or knowledge of human diversity through analysis of an issue.

Institutional Objective 4:

Integrate these abilities and capacities, adapting them to new settings, questions, and responsibilities.

ACE 10: Generate a creative or scholarly product that requires broad knowledge, appropriate technical proficiency, information collection, synthesis, interpretation, presentation, and reflection.

ACE Structural Criteria

Graduates of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln will satisfy the requirements of their majors, their colleges, and the ACE Program.

1. ACE courses are credit-bearing curricular offerings or equivalent documented co-curricular experiences.

2. The ACE Program will consist of the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes.

3. Any ACE course approved to satisfy an ACE Student Learning Outcome satisfies that Student Learning Outcome in all UNL undergraduate colleges.

4. Up to three ACE Student Learning Outcomes 4-10 may be satisfied by work in one subject area.

5. ACE Student Learning Outcomes must be satisfied by work in at least three subject areas.

6. No ACE course may satisfy more than one ACE Student Learning Outcome in a student’s program.

7. If an ACE course addressed two ACE Student Learning Outcomes, the student decides which one of the two Outcomes the course will satisfy in that student’s program.

8. Every ACE course will reinforce at least one of the following as appropriate for the discipline and as identified by the department offering the course: Writing, Oral Communication, Visual Literacy, Historical Perspectives, Mathematics and Statistics, Critical Thinking, Teamwork, Problem Solving, Ethics, Civics, Social Responsibility, Global Awareness, or Human Diversity.

ACE courses are identified in course descriptions by the ACE symbol followed by the Student Learning Outcome number(s) that they fulfill. See the ACE website at: http://ace.unl.edu for the most current information and the most recently certified courses.

Military Science/Army ROTC

Description

Chair: Lt. Col. James D. Lander

110 Pershing Military & Naval Science Building

http://www.unl.edu/armyrotc

Military Science/Army ROTC

Military Science is a United States Army ROTC program offered at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln through a cooperative effort contractually agreed to by the United States Army and the University.

Objectives

Prepare, graduate, and commission students with leadership potential to serve as commissioned officers in the United States Army, Army Reserve and National Guard components
Develop leadership skills, managerial skills and a basic understanding of associated professional knowledge with a strong sense of personal integrity, honor and individual responsibility

Benefits

Academic credits earned may apply toward the student’s degree depending on the discipline
Upon successful completion of the ROTC program and all bachelor degree requirements, students earn a commission as a Second Lieutenant in the United States Army concurrent with an academic degree in a discipline of choice
Receive leadership training designed to qualify graduates for civilian careers in executive and management positions upon completion of their military commitment
Uniforms, textbooks and equipment are provided to the student

Participation in Army ROTC

There are three basic ways to participate in Army ROTC:

1. Participating student:

Registers for basic military science classes in sequential order (101 through 202 only), but not the military science lab.
Is not allowed to participate in activities outside the classroom (physical training, leadership labs or field training).
Receives academic credit only; no credit towards commissioning.

2. Enrolled Cadet:

Fully participates in ROTC by taking the military science classes and leadership labs.
Participates in physical and field training exercises.
Wears the Army uniform to all ROTC functions.
Must adhere to military customs and standards.
Unless contracted, no military obligation is incurred (Basic Course only).

3. Contracted Cadet:

Like the enrolled Cadet, fully participates in military science classes, leadership labs, and physical and field training exercises; wears the army uniform to all ROTC functions; and adheres to military customs and standards.
Includes progression, lateral entry and scholarship Cadets.
Is under obligation of future military service to receive benefits from ROTC.
National and Campus Based ROTC scholarship winners must contract to receive stipend and scholarship benefits.
Non-scholarship Cadets must contract by the MS III/junior year in order to continue in the program.

Curriculum

Military science is an academic elective program, not an academic major. The overall curricula is designed and standardized by a national review process controlled by U.S. Army Cadet Command.

Four-year program:

The Army ROTC four-year program consists of two parts: Basic Course and Advanced Course.

Basic Course: One basic level military science course (MLSC 101, MLSC 102, MLSC 201, and MLSC 202) is taken each semester in conjunction with one lab session per week during the freshman and sophomore years. Students may participate in the Army ROTC basic level courses without incurring any military obligation.
Advanced Course: One advanced level military science course (MLSC 301, MLSC 302, MLSC 401, and MLSC 402) is taken each semester along with one lab session per week during the junior and senior years. Military science advanced courses may only be taken by students who are contracting to earn a commission and have completed Basic Course (or equivalency).

Two-year program:

The Army ROTC two-year program accommodates upper-class students already enrolled at or transferring to UNL who have not taken the Basic Course. To participate in this program, the student shall have successfully completed the Leader’s Training Course (LTC), Army Basic Combat Training, or alternate approved training during the summer before entering the Advanced Course.

Commissioning Requirements

Upon graduation with a degree from the University and successful completion of Army ROTC requirements, you will commission into the Army, Army Reserve, or Army National Guard as a Second Lieutenant. The requirements are:

Satisfactory completion of:

The Basic Course (via enrollment in the program and/or placement credit)
The Advanced Course
Leader Development and Assessment Course
A course in Military History (HIST 303 or HIST 304)

The cadet must:

Maintain at least a 2.0 cumulative grade point average (GPA).
Pass a Department of Defense medical examination within 24 months of the date of commissioning.
Pass the Army Physical Fitness Test within 30 days of the date of commissioning.
Not have exceeded the 32nd birthday (27th for scholarship students) by December 30 of the year of commissioning.

For information on financial assistance, Army ROTC scholarships, Army ROTC courses and general information about the UNL Army ROTC program, visit www.unl.edu/armyrotc.

Naval Science/Naval ROTC

Description

Chair: CAPT Richard Thomas

103 Pershing Military and Naval Science Building

http://www.unl.edu/nrotc/

The Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps (NROTC) is a competitive program designed for the purpose of educating men and women for service as commissioned officers in the United States Navy and Marine Corps. Students accepted into the program receive training and experience in the one quality that will always be in great demand: Leadership. Upon commissioning, University of Nebraska NROTC graduates serve in such diverse fields as aviation, surface warfare, submarine warfare, nursing, and as United States Marines.

Benefits

Navy NROTC Midshipmen may receive a national scholarship covering full tuition and fees, a stipend for books, and a monthly stipend to help cover living expenses.
There is also a non-scholarship program for students who did not initially qualify for a national scholarship but are interested in a career in the United States Navy or United States Marine Corps; they compete for other scholarships or must earn a scholarship by the end of their academic sophomore year.
All NROTC students receive their full uniform at no cost.
For information on financial assistance, Navy and Marine Corps ROTC Scholarships, and general information about the UNL Naval ROTC program, visit http://www.unl.edu/nrotc/.

Curriculum

Four-Year Scholarship Program

Four-Year NROTC scholarships are awarded annually based on a competitive selection process in which consideration is given to factors such as high school record, college board scores, extracurricular activities, and leadership qualities. The primary applicant to this program is a high school senior, but college freshman may also qualify.

Three-Year Scholarship Program

During their freshman year at UNL, students may apply for the national scholarship. It is recommended that students interested in this possibility enroll in NAVS classes and participate in battalion activities.

Two-Year Scholarship Program

Two-Year NROTC scholarships are awarded to current students that are approaching their junior year. Consideration is given to factors such as performance in college and leadership potential. Recipients of this scholarship may attend a six-week naval indoctrination program in Rhode Island the summer before their junior year.

College Program

The College Program is a non-scholarship program designed for students who did not qualify for an ROTC Scholarship. Students in the College Program are fully integrated in the NROTC program and qualify for the same careers in the Navy and Marine Corps upon graduation. There is also opportunity for College Program students to compete for NROTC scholarships after one or more semesters of exemplary performance.

Naval Science Open Curriculum

Any University of Nebraska–Lincoln student may take naval science academic courses for college credit. However, enrollment in leadership laboratories is restricted to students who are accepted into the NROTC program. No active duty obligation is incurred.

Individualized Program of Studies in Naval Science

It is possible to minor in naval science under the Individualized Program of Studies program in the College of Arts and Sciences. All College of Arts and Sciences students interested in the naval science major are eligible.

An individualized studies minor requires 24 credit hours, including 9 in one department and 12 within the College of Arts and Sciences. Approval of the program of studies must be obtained from the student’s arts and sciences adviser and endorsed by a representative of the dean of the College of Arts and Sciences.

NOTE: Although students may take additional naval science courses beyond the 12-credit-hour maximum, credits received in these courses will not count toward a degree in the College of Arts and Sciences.

Students enrolled in the NROTC program must take 23 credits in naval science subjects to earn a commission and should schedule all required classes prior to asking their College of Arts and Sciences adviser for approval of the Individualized Program of Studies.

Transfer

UNDERGRADUATE TRANSFER CREDIT POLICY

This statement outlines important information for students who present undergraduate credit for transfer to a degree program at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. Transfer credit is any post-secondary credit earned at an institution outside the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, including other institutions in the University of Nebraska System (NCTA, UNK, UNO, and UNMC).

The college within the University of Nebraska–Lincoln in which a student enrolls (the degree college) has ultimate responsibility for determining how all credit, including transfer credit, will apply to a specific degree program. Evaluation of transfer credit is based on a review of the comparability of the nature, content and level of the learning experience and its appropriateness to the student’s degree program. The acceptance and use of transfer credit are subject to limitations in accordance with the educational policies of The University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

TRANSFER CREDIT PRACTICES

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln endorses the Joint Statement on Transfer and Award of Academic Credit approved by the American Council on Education (ACE), the American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers (AACRAO), and the Council for Higher Education Accreditation (CHEA). The current issue of Transfer Credit Practices of Designated Educational Institutions, published by AACRAO is an example of a reference used in determining transfer credit.

Applicants must request an official transcript sent to the Office of Admissions from each college attended. Failure to provide transcripts from all colleges or universities attended may result in denial of the application or dismissal from the university. Grades from institutions outside the Universities in the NU System will be used for evaluation and admission, but will not become part of the University cumulative Grade Point Average (GPA). Each degree college determines its policy for acceptance and application of grades below C to degree requirements.

A. CREDIT PRESENTED FOR TRANSFER FROM WITHIN THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA SYSTEM

Credit earned at any institution within the University of Nebraska System will be accepted by UNL. Applicability to degree requirements is determined by the student’s degree college. Direct course equivalencies with UNK, UNO and UNMC, established by faculty, are maintained by the NU System and are available on-line at http://coursefinder.nebraska.edu. Applicability of courses without direct equivalencies will be at the discretion of the degree college.

B. INTER-INSTITUTIONAL AGREEMENTS

Associate to Baccalaureate Agreements. Agreements have been established for specific programs at selected community colleges.

Transfer courses equivalencies. Direct equivalencies have been established by UNL faculty for courses from a number of institutions including Nebraska Community Colleges and Nebraska College of Technical Agriculture. Applicability of courses without direct equivalencies will be at the discretion of the degree college. Transfer Course Equivalency tables are available on-line at http://admissions.unl.edu/nebraska/equivalency. While every effort is made to ensure accuracy, this information is subject to change.

C. CREDIT PRESENTED FOR TRANSFER WHICH REQUIRES ADDITIONAL REVIEW BY THE DEGREE COLLEGE

The following types of transfer credit require additional review by the student’s degree college within UNL to determine applicability to the student’s program of study.

Credit in courses presented for transfer which do not have a direct equivalent as established by UNL faculty.
Credit in courses determined by University of Nebraska–Lincoln to be of a developmental, vocational, or technical nature.
Credit in courses or programs in which the institution granting the credit is not directly involved.
Credit presented for transfer from institutions not accredited by one of the regional accrediting commissions. (www.chea.org)
In determining the acceptability of transfer credit from colleges which are not regionally accredited, acceptance practices indicated in the current issue of Transfer Credit Practices of Designated Educational Institutions, an AACRAO publication, will be used as a guide. For institutions not listed in the publication, guidance is requested from the designated reporting institution of the appropriate state.
Credit presented for transfer from institutions outside the United States. Transfer credit from foreign educational institutions may be granted after a determination of the type of institution involved, its recognition by the educational authorities of the foreign country, and an evaluation of the content, level, and comparability of the study to courses and programs at University of Nebraska–Lincoln. Credit may be granted in specific courses or assigned to general areas of study. Questions about foreign credentials and educational systems should be directed to the Office of Admissions.

SPECIAL SITUATIONS, QUALIFICATIONS, AND LIMITATIONS RELATED TO TRANSFER OF CREDIT

Applicability of transfer credit to degree requirements

The student’s degree college within the University of Nebraska–Lincoln has ultimate responsibility for determining how all credit, including transfer credit, will apply to a specific degree program.

Transfer credit from two-year or four-year institutions

No more than 60 semester or 90 quarter credits earned at two-year colleges can be applied to an undergraduate degree from University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

No more than 90 total hours may transfer from all institutions to the University of Nebraska-Lincoln for a degree program. Please consult the appropriate college section of the undergraduate Bulletin for college specific policies regarding transfer credit.

Lower division credit

Lower division courses transferred to UNL will generally be used to meet lower division requirements. In the event that a lower division transfer course is used as a substitution for an upper division requirement at the university a student may be required to complete additional upper division hours for graduation.

Residency requirement

The University’s colleges may require that specific courses or a certain number of credit hours be completed on the UNL campus to satisfy the residency requirement.

Dual Credit earned while a student is enrolled in high school

When a student earns both high school and college credit for a course, the student must present a transcript from the original postsecondary institution offering credit for the course. Such courses will be evaluated as transfer credit.

Other credit earned while in high school

Many students enroll in one or more college courses while enrolled in high school. An official transcript of all courses attempted must be presented upon application unless the credit was earned at UNL. Credit from institutions outside the University of Nebraska–Lincoln will be evaluated as transfer credit

Credit earned in the United States Armed Forces

Students with military service will be awarded 1 credit of military science for every three months of active duty up to a total of four credits. Credit for technical or specialized schools will be accepted to the extent that the material is applicable toward degree requirements at UNL.

Credit by Examination (CBE)

Programs accepted at University of Nebraska–Lincoln include the Advanced Placement (AP) Program, the International Baccalaureate (IB) Examinations, the College Level Examination Program (CLEP), and departmental examinations. For information on specific exams and required scores accepted for credit at UNL see: http://admissions.unl.edu/advanced. Credit by Exam (AP, IB, or CLEP credit) may not be transferred directly to University of Nebraska–Lincoln from another institution. However, the scores from these examinations may be sent to University of Nebraska–Lincoln from the testing agency, and credit will be awarded based on UNL’s AP, IB, and CLEP policies.

Students who anticipate applying to professional programs should inquire about the acceptability of Credit by Exam before registering for exams.

Credit by Departmental Examination

Credit by departmental examination allows regularly enrolled students to gain academic credit for knowledge they have acquired by self-study or experience. The student’s knowledge base is expected to parallel that of the specific UNL course for which the student wishes to gain credit. A fee of one-half of resident tuition is charged to administer and/or evaluate an examination for credit. Examinations for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive Credit by Examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken. Credit earned by examination is not applicable for use in an advanced degree program. Credit granted by another college for placement exams or locally designed test-out examinations will not be accepted in transfer.

University of Nebraska–Lincoln students who earn credit at another institution

Current UNL students are urged to consult with the appropriate academic adviser before enrolling in any course intended to be applied to the student’s degree. Non-UNL credit for education abroad programs will be evaluated as transfer credit upon receipt of official transcripts. Current UNL students who wish to enroll in a course at another institution in the NU System should file an Intercampus Application, http://admissions.unl.edu/apply/intercampus.asp.

University of Nebraska–Lincoln students who wish to transfer from one UNL college to another

Current UNL students seeking to gain admission to another degree college must meet all standards for admission to the new college as a transfer applicant. The new college will evaluate all of the student’s credit, including transfer credit, to determine which credit will be applicable to degree requirements.

University Honors Program

Description

http://honors.unl.edu/

The University Honors Program is a special program for which formal application is required. Students admitted to the Program have ACT composite scores in the upper 20s or above, are in the top ten percent of their high school class and, most importantly, have demonstrated a commitment to intellectual curiosity and academic excellence. Acceptance into the Program is based on a comprehensive evaluation of the student’s potential by the Honors Program Faculty Committee. All the undergraduate colleges support the Program, and honors courses apply to college and major requirements. A special notation is made on the transcript and diploma upon graduation from the University Honors Program to inform graduate schools and employers of the student’s superior performance. Honors Program students may request housing in the honors residence, the Neihardt Residence Center.

Students admitted to the Honors Program in their first year of college must fulfill the following requirements in order to complete the Program:

A. Full-time student: 12 credit hours each semester (fall and spring)

B. Cumulative GPA: 3.5

C. 24 credit hours in honors courses with a grade of B or better: to include 189H and 395H

D. Sequence:

First and Second years:

Complete 15 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better in the first four semesters of college work including 189H and file a Statement of Academic Interest.

Complete at least 6 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better each year (Fall and/or Spring).

Third and Fourth years:

Complete 9 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better in the junior and senior years, including 395H.

File a Memorandum of Study (research prospectus) prior to completing 100 hours.

Complete at least 3 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better each year (Fall or Spring)

E. Completion of an honors research or creative project (e.g., thesis).

Students admitted to the Program having earned college credits after high school graduation either at the University of Nebraska or another school should discuss modified requirements with the Honors Program director.

Students admitted to the University Honors Program have access to all honors courses taught at UNL without additional authorization.

NOTE: 189H Freshman Seminar is an honors course offered by participating academic departments. Required of all students in the University Honors Program.